# Daniel Emanuelsson, Ph.D.

Gothenburg, Sweden

d.emanuelsson@gmail.com

**4** +46 76 776 6740

S daniel.emanuelsson

https://nz.linkedin.com/in/demanuelsson
https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Daniel Emanuelsson

https://github.com/demanuelsson

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9373-6951



**Profile** 

I am a recent Victoria University of Wellington Earth Science doctorate. As a central part of multi-national teams and frontier research collaborations, I have gained extensive experience from several disciplines and my skills originate from both academia and client-oriented consulting. My research interests lie within the areas of climate dynamics; paleoclimatology; experimental design; laser spectroscopy; water stable isotopes; continuous flow analysis (CFA); decadal variability; tropical and midlatitude teleconnections with polar regions; atmosphere and sea-ice interactions; proxy/observational, data reanalysis/model comparisons; coastal and environmental processes; data analysis; and field campaigns.

### Skills

**Programming:** Advanced programming in Matlab, basic command of Python and Fortran.

Visualization: Matlab, GIS (ArcMap, esri).

**Analysis Skills:** Geospatial data-analysis in the area of climate science (e.g. utilizing reanalysis products, GCM output); time series analysis; statistical analysis; EOF analysis; spectral analysis; multiple linear regression analysis.

**Languages:** Excellent communication skills and proficiency in spoken and written English and Swedish (mother tongue).

Computer Platforms: Windows, Linux.

**Journal Reviews.** Acted as a reviewer for The Cryosphere.

## **Education**

9/2011–9/2016 Doctorate Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand

Doctoral Thesis Title: High-Resolution Water Stable Isotope Ice-Core

Record: Roosevelt Island, Antarctica.

Supervisors: Dr. Nancy A. N. Bertler, Prof. James A. Renwick, and Dr. W.

Troy Baisden

External Examiners: Dr. Nerillie J. Abram, Australian National University,

and Dr. Adrian J. McDonald, University of Canterbury.

9/2007–12/2008 University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA

Group of Prof. Paul D. Quay, Chemical Oceanography

Key courses from the University of Washington: Global Carbon Cycle and Greenhouse Gases, Atmospheric Chemistry, Climate Extremes, Limnology,

Advanced Aquatic Ecology, Lake and Watershed Management, Fluid

Dynamics.

9/2002-8/2007 Master of Science in Engineering, Environmental and Coastal

Engineer, Lund's University of Technology (LTH), Sweden

Master Thesis Title: Impact of Coastal Erosion and Sedimentation along the

Northern Coast of Sinai Peninsula Supervisor: Prof. Magnus Larson

Coauthor Ali Mirchi

Examiner Prof. Hans Hanson

In my MSc. thesis work, the predominant coastal processes affecting the erosion of the Sinai northern coastline were established using the GENESIS

model (a Fortran based sediment transport numerical model).

Key courses from LTH: Coastal Engineering, Statistics, Fluid Dynamics, Mathematics, Organic and Inorganic Chemistry, GIS Analysis, Aerosols Technology, Ecology, Thermodynamics, Groundwater, and Hydrology and

Hydrodynamics.

## Professional Employment

11/2016-3/2017 Isotope Biogeosciences, National Isotope Centre (NIC), GNS Science,

**New Zealand** 

Laboratory Technician

9/2011–9/2016 National Isotope Centre (NIC), GNS Science, New Zealand

PhD Student

Group of Dr. Nancy A. N. Bertler

1/2009-8/2011 **AECOM, Seattle, WA, US** 

Coastal and Environmental Engineer

Group of Jena Gilman P.E. Senior Coastal Engineer

Major Projects:

Coquille River Jetty Condition Evaluation, Bandon, Oregon. Owner U.S.

Army Corps of Engineers

Lower Duwamish Superfund Site, Seattle, Washington. Owner City of

Seattle

Inner Harbor Navigation Channel (IHNC) Hurricane Flood Protection, New

Orleans, Louisiana. Owner U.S. Army Corps of Engineer

6/2005–9/2007 Tomelilla Municipality, Sweden

GIS Analyst and Survey Technician

### Publications

Emanuelsson, B. D., N. A. N. Bertler, P. D. Neff, J. A. Renwick, B. R. Markle, W. T. Baisden, and E. D. Keller (2018a), The role of Amundsen–Bellingshausen Sea anticyclonic circulation in forcing marine air intrusions into West Antarctica, Clim. Dyn., doi: 10.1007/s00382-018-4097-3.

Emanuelsson, D. (2016), High-Resolution Water Stable Isotope Ice-Core Record: Roosevelt Island, Antarctica: a thesis submitted to the Victoria University of Wellington in fulfilment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy (Geology) / by B. Daniel Emanuelsson., Thesis (Ph.D.)--Victoria University of Wellington, 2016.

http://researcharchive.vuw.ac.nz/bitstream/handle/10063/6699/thesis\_access.pdf?sequence=4

Emanuelsson, B. D., W. T. Baisden, N. A. N. Bertler, E. D. Keller, and V. Gkinis (2015), High-resolution continuous-flow analysis setup for water isotopic measurement from ice cores using laser spectroscopy, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 8(7), 2869–2883, doi:10.5194/amt-8-2869-2015.

Tuohy, A., N. Bertler, P. Neff, R. Edwards, D. Emanuelsson, T. Beers, and P. Mayewski (2015), Transport and deposition of heavy metals in the Ross Sea Region, Antarctica, J. Geophys. Res. Atmos., 120(20), 10,11,911-996, doi:10.1002/2015JD023293.

Emanuelsson, B. D., J. Gilman, and J. Orlins (2011), Jetty Condition Evaluation Report for the Coquille River, Prep. U.S. Army Corps Eng., 126.

Emanuelsson, D., A. Mirchi, and M. Larson (2007), Impact of Coastal Erosion and Sedimentation along the Northern Coast of Sinai Peninsula, Lund's University of Technology (LTH).

#### Dr. Daniel Emanuelsson

d.emanuelsson@gmail.com

**□** +46 76 776 6740

### In prep.

Emanuelsson, B. D., J. A. Renwick, P. D. Neff, and N. A. N. Bertler (2018b), The Influence of Southern Hemisphere Climate Variability on Water Isotopes from the Roosevelt Island ice core, Antarctica, Preprint. <a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.7072664.v1">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.7072664.v1</a>

Emanuelsson, B. D., P. D. Neff, J. A. Renwick, and N. A. N. Bertler (2018c), The water isotopes (δD) from the Roosevelt Island ice core during the past millennium. In prep.

#### **Manuals**

Emanuelsson, D. (2017), Continuous vapor mode LGR manual Measuring water stable isotopes ( $\delta D$ ,  $\delta 18O$ ,  $\delta 17O$ ) using laser spectroscopy. [Research Report] GNS Science. 2017. <a href="https://hal.archivesouvertes.fr/hal-01847099">https://hal.archivesouvertes.fr/hal-01847099</a>

# Field and Lab Work Experience

2012, 2013, and 2014	RICE ice core processing continuous flow analysis (CFA) lab campaigns
11/2012- 1/2013	Roosevelt Island, Antarctica. RICE ice core drilling (0-130 m)
11/2011- 1/2012	Roosevelt Island, Antarctica. RICE ice core drilling (130-760 m)
9/2008	University of Washington's vessel R/V <i>Thomas G. Thompson</i> . Research cruise Seattle to Hawaii
1/2002-3/2002	Yacht Crew Member, Atlantic Ocean and Mediterranean Sea Crossing

## Scholarships

9/2011 9/2015	PhD Rutherford Schol	arship (Victoria	University of Wellington)
---------------	----------------------	------------------	---------------------------

9/2007– 12/2008 Valle Scholarship (University of Washington)

### International Conferences

12/2014	AGU conference	San	Francisco,	USA	(Poster)	
---------	----------------	-----	------------	-----	----------	--

8/2014 Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research (SCAR) conference (Talk)

# Memberships in Professional Associations

American Geophysical Union (AGU)

Association of Polar Early Career Scientists (APECS)

## Qualifications and Training

Driver's license: US, Sweden and New Zealand

Swedish coastal skipper certificate class VIII